window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Algorithms - Sorting",
  "duration": 130,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Sorting",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following array.<br><br>\\(\\begin{array}{|l|l|l|l|l|l|l|l|}  \\hline 23&amp;32&amp;45&amp;69&amp;72&amp;73&amp;89&amp;97 \\\\ \\hline\\end{array}\\)<br><br>\nWhich algorithm out of the following options uses the least number of comparisons (among the array elements) to sort the above array in ascending order? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Selection sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Mergesort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Insertion sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Quicksort using the last element as pivot</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Insertion sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357443/gate-cse-2021-set-1-question-9#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Of the following sort algorithms, which has execution time that is least dependant on initial ordering of the input? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Insertion sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Quick sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Merge sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Selection sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Merge sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331259/isro2020-65\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>An array of 25 distinct elements is to be sorted using quicksort. Assume that the pivot element is chosen uniformly at random. The probability that the pivot element gets placed in the worst possible location in the first round of partitioning (rounded off to 2 decimal places) is _________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.08",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302828/gate2019-cs-20#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Of the following sorting algorithms, which has a running time that is least dependent on the initial ordering of the input? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Mege Sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Insertion Sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Selection Sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Quick Sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Mege Sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213522/isro2018-66\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Given two sorted list of size m and n respectively. The number of comparisons needed the worst case by the merge sort algorithm will be: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>m-n</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>maximum of m and n</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>minimum of m and n</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>m+n-1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>m+n-1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213553/isro2018-35\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The number of swappings needed to sort the numbers 8 , 22, 7, 9, 31, 5, 13 in ascending order using bubble sort is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>11</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>12</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>13</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>10</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>10</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128694/isro2017-49\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following in-place sorting algorithms needs the minimum number of swaps? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Insertion Sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Quick Sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Heap Sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Selection Sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Selection Sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128545/isro2017-15\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Algorithm design technique used in quicksort algorithm is? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2016)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Dynamic programming</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Backtracking</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Divide and conquer</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Greedy method</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Divide and conquer</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2462/gate1994-1-19-isro2016-31\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Assume that the algorithms considered here sort the input sequences in ascending order. If the input is already in ascending order, which of the following are TRUE? <br>\nI. Quicksort runs in \\(\\Theta (n^{2})\\) time  <br>\nII. Bubblesort runs in \\(\\Theta (n^{2})\\) time <br>\nIII. Merge sort runs in \\(\\Theta (n)\\) time <br>\nIV. Insertion sort runs in \\(\\Theta (n)\\) time <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and II only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39561/gate2016-2-13#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>The worst case running times of Insertion sort, Mergesort and Quicksort, respectively, are: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta\\)(n logn), \\(\\Theta\\)(n logn), and \\(\\Theta(n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n^{2}),\\Theta(n^{2}), and \\Theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n^{2}),\\Theta(n logn), and \\Theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n^{2}),\\Theta(n logn), and \\Theta (n^{2})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n^{2}),\\Theta(n logn), and \\Theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39660/gate2016-1-13#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>If one uses straight two-way merge sort algorithm to sort the following elements in ascending order:<br>20, 47, 15, 8, 9, 4, 40, 30, 12, 17<br>then the order of these elements after second pass of the algorithm is: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>8, 9, 15, 20, 47, 4, 12, 17, 30, 40</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>8, 15, 20, 47, 4, 9, 30, 40, 12, 17</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>15, 20, 47, 4, 8, 9, 12, 30, 40, 17</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4, 8, 9, 15, 20, 47, 12, 17, 30, 40</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>8, 15, 20, 47, 4, 9, 30, 40, 12, 17</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1467/gate1999-1-14-isro2015-42\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>A machine needs a minimum of 100 sec to sort 1000 names by quick sort. The minimum time needed to sort 100 names will be approximately <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>50.2 sec</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>6.7 sec</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>72.7 sec</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>11.2 sec</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>6.7 sec</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/10595/isro2015-12\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Assume that a mergesort algorithm in the worst case takes 30 seconds for an input of size 64. Which of the following most closely approximates the maximum input size of a problem that can be solved in 6 minutes? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>256</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>512</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1024</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2048</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>512</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8480/gate2015-3-27#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Suppose you are provided with the following function declaration in the C programming language.<br><br> int partition(int a[ ], int n); <br><br> The function treats the first element of a[] as a pivot, and rearranges the array so that all elements less than or equal to the pivot is in the left part of the array, and all elements greater than the pivot is in the right part. In addition, it moves the pivot so that the pivot is the last element of the left part. The return value is the number of elements in the left part. <br>\nThe following partially given function in the C programming language is used to find the \\( k^{th}\\) smallest element in an array a[ ] of size n using the partition function. We assume \\( k \\leq n\\)<pre><code>  int kth_smallest(int a[], int n, int k)\n{\n    int left_end = partition(a,n);\n    if ( left_end+1 == k ){\n         return a[left_end];\n    }\n    if ( left_end+1 &gt; k ){\n         return kth_smallest( ________ );\n    } else {\n         return kth_smallest( ________ );\n    }\n} </code></pre><br> The missing argument lists are respectively <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(a, left_end, k) and (a+left_end+1, n-left_end-1, k-left_end-1)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(a, left_end, k) and (a, n-left_end-1, k-left_end-1)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(a+left_end+1, n-left_end-1, k-left_end-1) and (a, left_end, k)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(a, n-left_end-1, k-left_end-1) and (a, left_end, k)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>(a, left_end, k) and (a+left_end+1, n-left_end-1, k-left_end-1)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8243/gate2015-2-39#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following is the recurrence equation for the worst case time complexity of the Quicksort algorithm for sorting n ( \\(\\geq\\)2) numbers? In the recurrence equations given in the options below, c is a constant. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>T(n)=2T(n/2)+cn</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>T(n)=T(n-1)+T(1)+cn</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>T(n)=2T(n-1)+cn</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>T(n)=T(n/2)+cn</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>T(n)=T(n-1)+T(1)+cn</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8017/gate2015-1-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 16,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following sorting algorithms.<br>I.\nQuicksort<br>II.  Heapsort<br>III&gt; Mergesort<br>Which of them perform in least time in the worst case? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and II only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>III only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I, II and III</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/55014/isro2014-62\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 17,
          "question": "<p>You have an array of n elements. Suppose you implement quick sort by always choosing the central element of the array as the pivot. Then the tightest upper bound for the worst case performance is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O(n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n^{3})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(n^{2})\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2048/gate2014-3-14#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 18,
          "question": "<p>Let P be a quick sort program to sort numbers in ascending order using the first element as\nthe pivot. Let t1 and t2 be the number of comparisons made by P for the inputs [1 2 3 4\n5] and [4 1 5 3 2] respectively. Which one of the following holds? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(t_{1}=5\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\lt t_{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\gt t_{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(t_{1}=t_{2}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\gt t_{2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1780/gate2014-1-14#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 19,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following sorting algorithms has the minimum running time complexity in the best and average case? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Insertion sort, Quick sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Quick sort, Quick sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Quick sort, Insertion sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Insertion sort, Insertion sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Insertion sort, Quick sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43802/isro-2013-12\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 20,
          "question": "<p>The number of elements that can be sorted in \\(\\Theta (log n)\\) time using heap sort is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (1)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\sqrt{logn})\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\frac{log n}{log log n})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (log n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\frac{log n}{log log n})\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1541/gate2013-30#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 21,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following is the tightest upper bound that represents the number of swaps\nrequired to sort n numbers using selection sort? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>O(log n)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>O(n)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>O(n log n)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n^{2})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>O(n)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1415/gate2013-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 22,
          "question": "<p>A list of n strings, each of length n, is sorted into lexicographic order using the merge-sort\nalgorithm. The worst case running time of this computation is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>O (n log n)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>O (\\(n^{2} log n\\))</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>O (\\(n^{2}+ log n\\))</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>O (\\(n^{2}\\))</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>O (\\(n^{2} log n\\))</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1762/gate2012-39#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 23,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following algorithm design technique is used in merge sort? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Greedy method</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Backtracking</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Dynamic programming</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Divide and Conquer</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Divide and Conquer</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52859/isro2011-66\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 24,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following in place sorting algorithms needs the minimum number of swaps? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Quick sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Insertion sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Selection sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Heap sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Selection sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/975/gate2006-14-isro2011-14\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 25,
          "question": "<p>In quick sort, for sorting n elements, the (n/4)th smallest element is selected as\npivot using an O(n) time algorithm. What is the worst case time complexity of the quick sort? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n^{2} logn)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1325/gate2009-39#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 26,
          "question": "<p>What is the number of swaps required to sort n elements using selection sort, in the worst case? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n^{2} logn)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1303/gate2009-11#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 27,
          "question": "<p>How many comparisons are needed to sort an array of length 5 if a straight selection sort is used  and array is already in the opposite order? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>15</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>20</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>10</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/17268/isro2008-77\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 28,
          "question": "<p>If we use Radix Sort to sort n integers in the range \\(\\left (n^{k/2}, n^k \\right )\\), for some k&gt;0 which is independent of n, the time taken would be? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(kn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(n \\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(n^2)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(n \\log n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3353/gate2008-it-43\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 29,
          "question": "<p>Consider the Quicksort algorithm. Suppose there is a procedure for finding a pivot element which splits the list into two sub-lists each of which contains at least one-fifth of the elements. Let T(n) be the number of comparisons required to sort n elements. Then <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(T(n)\\leq 2T (n/5)+n\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n)\\leq T (n/5)+T(4n/5)+n\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(T(n)\\leq 2T (4n/5)+n\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(T(n)\\leq 2T (n/2)+n\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n)\\leq T (n/5)+T(4n/5)+n\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/455/gate2008-43#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 30,
          "question": "<p>The average case and worst case complexities for Merge sort algorithm are <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O (n^2), O  (n^2)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O  (n^2), O (n \\log_2 n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O (n \\log_2 n), O  (n^2)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n \\log_2 n), O (n \\log_2 n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n \\log_2 n), O (n \\log_2 n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/49624/isro2007-58\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 31,
          "question": "<p>Selection sort algorithm design technique is an example of <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Greedy method</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Divide-and-conquer</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Dynamic Programming</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Backtracking</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Greedy method</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/49537/isro2007-55\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 32,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following sorting algorithms has the lowest worst-case complexity? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Merge sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Bubble sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Quick sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Selection sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Merge sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1212/gate2007-14#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 33,
          "question": "<p>The median of n elements can be found in O(n) time. Which one of the following\nis correct about the complexity of quick sort, in which median is selected as pivot? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\theta\\)(n)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\theta\\)(nlogn)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n^{3})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\theta\\)(nlogn)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1830/gate2006-52#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 34,
          "question": "<p>Which one the following in place sorting algorithms needs the minimum number\nof swaps? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Quick-sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Insertion sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Selection sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Heap sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Selection sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/975/gate2006-14#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 35,
          "question": "<p>The tightest lower bound on the number of comparisons, in the worst case, for comparison-based\nsorting is of the order of <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>n</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(n^{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>nlogn</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(nlog^{2}n\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>nlogn</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1026/gate2004-29#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 36,
          "question": "<p>In a permutation \\(a_1.....a_n\\) of n distinct integers, an inversion is a pair  \\((a_i, a_j) \\) such that \\(i \\lt j\\) and \\(a_i \\gt a_j\\). <br><br> What would be the worst case time complexity of the insertion Sort algorithm, if\nthe inputs are restricted to permutations of 1....n with at most n inversions? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (nlogn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n^{1.5})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43576/gate2003-62#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 37,
          "question": "<p>The usual \\(\\Theta (n^{2})\\)  implementation of Insertion Sort to sort ab array uses linear\nsearch to identify the position where an element is to be inserted into the already\nsorted part of the array. If, instead, we use binary search to identify the position,\nthe worst case running time will <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>remain \\(\\Theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>become \\(\\Theta (n(logn)^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>become\\(\\Theta\\)(nogn)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>become\\(\\Theta\\)(n)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>remain \\(\\Theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/912/gate2003-22#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 38,
          "question": "<p>If one uses straight two-way merge sort algorithm to sort the following elements in ascending order:<br>\n20, 47, 15, 8, 9, 4, 40, 30, 12, 17<br>\nthen the order of these elements after second pass of the algorithm is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>8, 9, 15, 20, 47, 4, 12, 17, 30, 40</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>8, 15, 20, 47, 4, 9, 30, 40, 12, 17</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>15, 20, 47, 4, 8, 9, 12, 30, 40, 17</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4, 8, 9, 15, 20, 47, 12, 17, 30, 40</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>8, 15, 20, 47, 4, 9, 30, 40, 12, 17</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1467/gate1999-1-14-isro2015-42\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 39,
          "question": "<p>A sorting technique is called stable if <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>it takes \\(O (n \\log n)\\) time</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>it maintains the relative order of occurrence of non-distinct elements</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>it uses divide and conquer paradigm</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>it takes O(n) space</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>it maintains the relative order of occurrence of non-distinct elements</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1465/gate1999-1-12\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 40,
          "question": "<p>Give the correct matching for the following pairs: <br>\\(\\begin{array}{ll|ll}\\hline \\text{(A)} &amp; \\text{$O (\\log n)$} &amp; \\text{(P)} &amp; \\text{Selection sort} \\\\\\hline \\text{(B)} &amp; \\text{$O (n)$} &amp; \\text{(Q)}&amp; \\text{Insertion sort} \\\\\\hline \\text{(C)}&amp; \\text{$O (n \\log n)$} &amp; \\text{(R)} &amp; \\text{Binary search} \\\\\\hline \\text{(D)} &amp; \\text{$O (n^2)$} &amp;\\text{(S)} &amp; \\text{Merge sort} \\\\\\hline \\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A-R  B-P  C-Q  D-S</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A-R  B-P  C-S  D-Q</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>A-P  B-R  C-S  D-Q</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>A-P  B-S  C-R  D-Q</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>A-R  B-P  C-S  D-Q</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1659/gate1998-1-22\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 41,
          "question": "<p>Quick-sort is run on two inputs shown below to sort in ascending order taking first element as pivot <br>\n(i).  \\(1, 2, 3, \\dots n\\)<br>\n(ii). \\(n, n-1, n-2, \\dots, 2, 1\\)<br>\nLet \\(C_1\\) and \\(C_2\\) be the number of comparisons made for the inputs (i) and (ii) respectively. Then, <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(C_1 \\lt C_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(C_1 = C_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(C_1 \\gt C_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>we cannot say anything for arbitrary n</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(C_1 = C_2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2744/gate1996-2-15\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 42,
          "question": "<p>Merge sort uses: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Divide and conquer strategy</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Backtracking approach</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Heuristic search</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Greedy approach</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Divide and conquer strategy</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2592/gate1995-1-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 43,
          "question": "<p>Algorithm design technique used in quicksort algorithm is? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1994)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Dynamic programming</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Backtracking</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Divide and conquer</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Greedy method</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Divide and conquer</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2462/gate1994-1-19-isro2016-31\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 44,
          "question": "<p>Randomized quicksort is an extension of quicksort where the pivot is chosen\nrandomly. What is the worst case complexity of sorting n numbers using\nrandomized quicksort ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2001)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>O(n)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>O(nlogn)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>O(\\(n^{2}\\)\n)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>O(n!)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>O(\\(n^{2}\\)\n)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/707/gate2001-1-14#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 45,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (more than one may be correct) and write the corresponding letters only: <br>\nFollowing algorithm(s) can be used to sort n in the range \\([1\\ldots n^3]\\) in O(n) time <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1992)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Heap sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Quick sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Merge sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Radix sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Radix sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/559/gate1992-02-ix\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 46,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (More than one may be correct).<br>The complexity of comparision based sorting algorithms is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1990)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n \\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta \\left(n^2\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n\\sqrt n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n \\log n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/84830/gate1990-3-v\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 47,
          "question": "<p>Let P be a quicksort program to sort numbers in ascending order. Let \\(t_{1}\\) and \\(t_{2}\\) be the time taken by the program for the inputs \\(\\left[1 \\ 2 \\ 3 \\ 4\\right]\\) and \\(\\left[5 \\ 4 \\ 3 \\ 2 \\ 1\\right]\\), respectively. Which of the following holds? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1987)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} = t_{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\gt t_{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\lt t_{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(t_{1}=t_{2}+5 \\log 5\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\lt t_{2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/80366/gate1987-1-xviii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
